Alright בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*.
Today's דף daf, *Daf* is officially מא *Mem Aleph*. We're 41. We're
a little bit behind. We pick up at the bottom of מא
עמוד amud ב *Mem Aleph Amud Bet*. We had just done the
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. We're in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right after the
משנה Mishna, *Mishna*. We had just done the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* that
said moved on to the other payments by the case of rape,
and we have בושת boshet, *Boshet* and פגם pegam. *Pagam* as well
as צער tzaar, *Tza'ar*, although interestingly צער tzaar *Tza'ar* is not going
to be addressed. And by בושת boshet *Boshet* it goes according to
the degree of embarrassment based on the person doing the embarrassment and
the person embarrassed, and the פגם pegam *Pagam* goes by the slave
market and it repeated the idea that the קנס knas *Knas*, the
50 שקל shekel *Shekel*, was fixed for everyone. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* right afterwards at the very bottom of מא עמוד א *Mem
Aleph Amud Aleph*, ואימא *Ve-eima* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, חמישים *Chamishim*
צלויי אמרה רחמנא מכל מילי *Tzloy amara Rachmana mikol mili*. How do
you know that you pay these additional payments that you normally pay
for assault? How do you know you pay it in addition to
the 50 שקל shekel *Shekel*? Maybe the 50 שקל shekel *Shekel* covers
all of that. אמר amar רבי זירא *Amar Rabbi Zeira* אמרו *Amru*
because people will say, no just look at it logically. בת מלכים
חמישים בת הדיוט חמישים *Bat melachim chamishim, bat hedyot chamishim*? If this
guy basically has sex with, but
obviously talking about, but it would also apply to the case of
seduction. But anyway, so if he rapes a princess, he pays 50,
the daughter of a king, and if he rapes, you know, somebody
from a high status, that's what he pays and if he rapes
somebody a lay person, a daughter of a lay person, he pays
50? Meaning it's crazy that there should be just one payment and
it wouldn't make a difference based on the actual amount of shame
and injury and so on that was done. There would be no
fairness to it. אמר ליה Amar leih, אביי Abaye *Amar lei Abaye*,
so Abaye said back to this, אי הכי *Ei hachi*, if that's
true, גבי עבד eved, נמי *gabei eved nami*. So how about another
place where the תורה Torah *Torah* sets a fixed amount and there
we don't look at differences. It says אמרו לו *Amru lo* when
an ox gores a slave, he pays 30 שקל shekel *Shekel*. So
אמרו *Amru* will people say עבד eved נוקב מרגליות שלושים *Eved nokev
margaliyot shloshim*? If you have a slave that's able to basically make
holes in pearls, okay, you have a slave that could earn a
thousand dollars an hour and an ox gored it and all you
do is pay 30 שקל shekel *Shekel*. עבד eved עושה מעשה מחט
*Eved oseh ma'aseh machat* and you have another slave that all he
can do is he's a tailor, makes two dollars an hour and
also שלושים *shloshim* 30 שקל shekel *Shekel*?
So there's unfairness there too, but there are times the תורה Torah
*Torah* sets a fixed amount, so here too maybe the תורה Torah
*Torah* sets a fixed amount. אלא אמר amar רבי זירא *Ela amar
Rabbi Zeira*, okay, so Rabbi Zeira will just says okay, consider the
following though, contrast, not about the question about social standing but the
following difference. אילו בא עליה שנים *Ilu ba aleha shnayim*, if two
people rape her, אחד כדרכה ואחד שלא כדרכה *echad ke-darkah ve-echad shelo
ke-darkah*. The first one not in the natural way, meaning anal sex,
and the next one natural, or could it be as תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos* points out the second one, first one is natural.
Oh well, the language here is that way, but it means the
order I said, okay.
Yeah, how do you know that?
Because of the point the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s making and תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos* says that explicitly. As I'll say, so the point being because
we want the second one to be paying 50 שקל shekel. *Shekel*
as well. So if the first one raped her, you know, through
vaginal intercourse then she would no longer be a נערה na'arah. בתולה
betula *na'ara betulah* and then the second one wouldn't pay. But interestingly
for the purposes of נערה na'arah, בתולה betulah *na'ara betulah* for the
50 שקל shekel. *Shekel*, if she actually has had sex and it's
anal sex and it did not rupture the hymen, didn't have the
potential of rupturing the hymen, she is still considered a בתולה *betulah*
for the הלכה Halacha *halacha* of the 50 שקל shekel, *Shekel*. So
therefore, if in this scenario where the first one raped her שלא
כדרכה *shelo ke-darkah* anally and the second one really doesn't matter which
way, so but that's why the second one is also paying 50
שקל shekel *Shekel*. So he's, so the point is so you have
these two people for the same, raping the same woman paying 50
שקל shekel. *Shekel*. So will they say יאמרו *Yomru* will people say
בא שלמה חמישים בא פגומה חמישים *Ba shleimah chamishim, ba pegumah chamishim*?
That the guy who, you know, raped the woman that was a
full woman as it were, a woman who had never had sex,
pays 50 and the next guy also pays 50? That would be
crazy, that wouldn't be logical. The funny thing of course is here
besides of course the horrific scenario that the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* describes,
but the strange thing is why is that better than the earlier
question? I mean basically it's just saying you know and if anything
for us this is more disturbing, like it's one thing to say
you know woman of high status, it was a greater injury, this
and that. Here it's like it's not so clear why there should
be such a difference based on whether you know this woman had
sex before even if she wasn't or was raped before even if
she wasn't or you know and therefore no longer was no longer
a בתולה *betulah*.
That that should somehow obviously mean that the amount of the fine
is going to be less.
So I understand the different framing.
The primary difference of the framing is not that from our sense
that there's a logic it should be less money, but it seems
to be from our perspective I think if anything the first question
was a much better one, but it's that this has to do
with the physical state of her body. So maybe the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* assumes that since her physical state of her body is different
that therefore it's more obvious that there should be a difference. to
be a difference in terms of payment. So אמר amar ליה אביי,
Abaye אביי said back to this, אי הכי גבי עבד נמי. i
hachi gabei eved nami. So so what? Make the same argument by
the slave when the ox gores it? יאמר עבד בריא שלושים עבד
מוכה שחין שלושים. yomar eved bari shloshim eved mukeh shechin shloshim.
Let's say you have nice healthy, you know, physically fit עבד, eved
and you have another one that's, you know, that's that's diseased and,
you know, and whatever,
right right right right right's weak and diseased and covered with boils
and whatever, so that also is the same amount. So basically by
the עבד eved. you have an example that regardless of the person's
social standing or or, you know, financial you know ability
to earn potential or physical state, it's going to be the same
amount for one עבד eved, and the next. So therefore if it
starts at 50 שקל shekel, by this case of rape, maybe it's
the same regardless of the woman's status. How do you know that
there are differences beyond the קנס Kenas, based on, you know, בושת
ופגם? boshet u'fgam? Maybe it's the 50 covers everything and no difference
based on the person. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's the
question. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye,
so אביי says here, we get it from a פסוק. pasuk. We
don't get it from a purely logical argument, we get it from
a פסוק. pasuk. אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, אמר קרא amar
kra says, תחת אשר ענה, tachat asher ina, that you should pay
the 50 שקל shekel in exchange for that he has oppressed, you
know, raped this woman. הני תחת אשר ענה, hani tachat asher ina,
the 50 שקל shekel. is for the act of rape, for the
act of intercourse, forceful intercourse, מכלל דאיכא בושת ופגם, michlal d'ika boshet
u'fgam, there are other payments that are for other things, not just
for the act of forceful intercourse itself, but for the associated embarrassment
and devaluing of the woman and so on. רבא אמר אמר קרא,
Rava amar amar kra, רבא Rava learns it from another verse. The
verse says ונתן האיש השוכב עמה לאבי הנערה חמישים כסף, v'natan ha'ish
hashochev imah l'avi hana'arah chamishim kasef,
the man who sleeps with her shall pay to the father 50
כסף. kesef. So it says, it combines sleeping with her and the
payment. So הנאת שכיבה, hana'at shchiva, the payment for the pleasure of
sex is 50. מכלל דאיכא בושת ופגם, michlal d'ika boshet u'fgam, to
tell you that there's other payments, the payments of embarrassment and and
damages. So basically they just say that the 50 in the תורה
Torah is for the act of intercourse and not for the associated
other types of injuries that occur or damage that occurs. Of course,
again, it's just from our perspective, the way of describing this as
הנאת שכיבה, hana'at shchiva, the pleasure of the act of sex, I
mean maybe from the rapist's perspective, but but yes I understand, still
though it's a little troubling. Anyway, the 50 שקל shekel. is for
the act of sex per se and for the act of rape
per se but not for the associated injuries and damages and so
on. Now the גמרא Gemara moves on, so that's how we know
the idea that there's these other payments as well. So now the
גמרא Gemara goes on with another question. ואימא לדידה, v'eima l'didah, how
do you know, because the תורה Torah says the 50 שקל shekel
goes to the father. It doesn't say, now that you've sort of
inferred that there are these other payments, the תורה Torah doesn't say
where they go, maybe the בושת ופגם boshet u'fgam goes to the
woman. Now the obvious answer to this that תוספות Tosafot already points
out is, is that and the גמרא's Gemara going to more or
less point out later, is that you know it can't go to
the woman, because if it goes to the woman then in the
case of פיתוי, pituy, in the case of seduction, there would be
no payment because if fundamentally the woman deserves it then when she's
doing it consensually there would be no payment, I mean there'd be
the 50 שקל shekel because that's the father, but but there would
be no payment to her for the פיתוי pituy and for the
בושת ופגם, boshet u'fgam, she's consenting. The fact that we have those
payments in the case of פיתוי, pituy, in the case of seduction,
proves that they are the father's payments and therefore even if the
girl consents, the father didn't consent and therefore those payments are still
going to take place. So that's how we know that the משנה
Mishnah assumes that that it goes straight to the father. But what
we want to know is how do we learn it from the
פסוק? pasuk? Right once we're asserting now that there's these other payments
implicit in the פסוק pasuk or the פסוק pasuk is only talking
about one aspect but there would always naturally be these other payments
because it's an act of injury, what's our basis based on the
verse to say that that goes to the father? Maybe it should
go to her. So the גמרא Gemara says, so ואימא
לדידה, v'eima l'didah, maybe it goes to her. אמר קרא amar kra
says, בנעוריה בית אביה, b'neureha beit aviha,
a verse by the annulment of vows, it says that the father
annuls the vows when she is in her youth in the father's
house. So from there we try to make a general principle that
it's not just about annulling vows. כל שבח נעורים לאביה. kol shevach
neurim l'aviha.
All benefits that come from נעורים, neurim, all benefits that come from
her youth go to the father. So any type of you know
money or power or control vis-à-vis her is her father's while she's
still a נערה. na'ara, So therefore these are damages, these would go
to the father, not just the 50 שקל. shekel So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא הא דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, ela ha d'amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, so that what רב הונא Rav Huna said
in the name of רב, Rav, מניין שמעשה בת לאביה, minayin she'ma'aseh
bat l'aviha, how do you know that if a daughter earns money
while she's still a קטנה ktana or a נערה, na'ara. how do
you know it goes to the father? שנאמר she'ne'emar the verse says...
So
מה אמה מעשה ידיה לרבה? mah amah ma'aseh yadeha lerabbah? So the
same way, so it compares the daughter to a slave, so the
same way a slave her earnings go to her master, whatever she
produces with her hands go to her master, אף בת מעשה ידיה
לאביה. af bat ma'aseh yadeha le'aviha. So similarly by a girl, anything
she produces, any earnings go to the father. Of course you could
say that that is not only גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, the fact
that he can sell her as a slave, and the reason why
you sell somebody as a slave is that the master can benefit
from the person's work, means shows that the father actually owns her
work, which is what allows him to sell her for that purposes
to another master.
So he is the master then.
He is the master before he sells her to another master, right,
before he sells her to another master. So there you see that
her earnings go to the father. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says
if that, so that is a pretty good learning derivation from that
verse. But the גמרא Gemara says but on you, but according to
you, תיפוק לי מבינעוריה בית אביה. teipuk li mibine'ureha beit aviha. If
you try to say that this verse by vows, annulling vows, is
a general teaches you a general rule that the father has total
control and rights to his daughter. But that is not true because
then we would not have needed to learn that his rights to
her earnings from this other verse of selling her as a slave.
The fact that we learn that he has rights to her earnings
from this verse of selling her as a slave shows that there
is not a big general umbrella rule that he gets all of
the benefits that derive from her. And why is that? Why don't
we learn it from the verse בינעוריה? bine'ureha? So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא ההוא בהפרת נדרים הוא דכתיב. ella hahu behafarat nedarim hu
dechtiv.
That verse of in her youth in her father's house is specifically
about his right to annul her vows. וכי תימא נלף מיניה, vechi
teima neilef mineih, okay, but let's use that as a paradigm and
apply, if he can annul her vows, maybe he has all rights
to her. No, ממונא
מאיסורא לא ילפינן. mamona me'issura lo yalfinan. Rights about איסור, issur, about
things like vows, about obligations and transgressions, do not necessarily translate into
things that are true about monetary rights. So we don't know from
there. So from the first בינעוריה בית אביה bine'ureha beit aviha you
only know he has the right to annul the vows. From the
verse of וכי ימכור איש את בתו לאמה vechi yimkor ish et
bito le'amah that he can sell her as a slave, you know
he has the rights to the earnings. But what you don't know
is that he has the rights that derive from injury done to
her person. And as תוספות Tosafot points out, that is a little
bit different than just her earnings. It is one thing to say
monetary purposes, she earns money, the father gets it, fine, you go
to a work, you earn money. But an injury actually done to
your person, maybe that is something that the תורה Torah would say
that you deserve to get paid for that directly, not the father.
So we don't know it from either of these two verses. Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכי תימא נלף מקנסא, vechi
teima neilef miknasa,
and let's learn out from the fact that okay the father gets
the fifty שקל. No, ממונא מקנסא לא ילפינן. mamona miknasa lo yalfinan.
קנס, knas. a fine, is always seen as an exception. So even
though he gets the father gets the fifty שקל, that doesn't mean
he gets the monetary payment that are payments for personal injury. So
we know he gets the fine, we know he gets her earnings,
we know he is allowed to annul the vows. But how do
we know he gets the payments for personal injury? So the גמרא
Gemara says אלא מסתברא דאביה הוו. ella mistavra de'aviha havu.
No, it actually here is how come we can assume that the
father gets those, ואי בעי מסר לה למנוול ולמוכת שחין, ve'i ba'ei
masar lah lemenuvval ulemukat shechin,
because he actually does have power over these things as well. How
does he have the power? He can decide who to marry her
off to. So the problem is now why are there these other
payments? There's these other payments for בושת, boshet the embarrassment,
and
for פגם. pegam. The פגם pegam is that she's no longer a
virgin. So the father can control that. He can marry her off
and that will mean that she will become no longer a virgin.
So any payment that comes as a result of her no longer
being a virgin is something he had control over. How about the
issue of shame? Well, the father can marry her off to a
disgusting person which will bring her a lot of shame. So since
he has control over her shame, therefore he gets paid for it.
Now of course what's funny about that is that again not distinguishing
between the shame about being married to somebody of let's say a
lowly status as opposed to the shame of being raped, number one.
Okay, number two is that there is also the whole question that
we have been asking is about who is shamed? Is it the
girl who is shamed? So then how is there a payment when
she does it consensually? Are we saying that she is shamed even
if she is willing to be shamed? It seems like we're saying
that because it doesn't seem like we're talking about the shame of
the father, because then it would be more obvious if it was
about the shame of the father that he got that shame and
he should be paid for it directly. Okay, but we presumably don't
say that. We say shame is only paid to the person who
is injured. So it is only paid to the girl. So that
just leads to the funny example that even in the case of
consensual sex, of seduction, we still say that there's a payment of
shame, that she is considered to have been shamed even though she
agreed to it willingly. That is just one interesting point. So she
is the one who is shamed, she is the one who becomes
not a virgin, the father can bring similar statuses on her, not
virgin yes, not the exact same type of shame, and therefore we
say he is in control of that and therefore he gets the
payment. The other thing however that is not addressing is that by
the case of rape there's also a payment. The other thing however
that is not addressing is that by the case of rape there's
also a payment of צער, tzaar, of suffering. And you know, again,
the father can maybe marry her off to a man and she'll
have some צער when she has that first act of sex, but
that gets us back to the early גמרא Gemara that basically was,
you know, was having a hard time understanding why there's more pain
and suffering by rape than by consensual sex, which was obviously a
challenging, a difficult גמרא. Gemara But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara conceded that
there was, so it's still not exactly clear why he gets the
payment of צער, right? He doesn't presumably marry her off in order
to be raped by her husband. So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara
sort of says based on the ideas that he has all of
this complete control over her, it makes sense to say that once
we say she does get these payments, that the payments do go
to the father. One minute, let's just finish up to the משנה,
Mishnah פגם אונס כאילו היא שפחה נמכרת, Pegam ones k’ilu hi shifcha
nimkeret, when you figure out the damages, you determine it based as
if she was a woman being sold like you normally determine any
damages, based on the slave market. So the גמרא Gemara. says היכי
שיימינן לה? Heichi shaminnan lah? How do we evaluate her? אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, אומדים, omdin, we estimate
כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בין שפחה בתולה לשפחה בעולה לשמשה. kama adam
rotzeh liten bein shifcha betulah l’shifcha beulah l’shamshah. How much would a
person pay for a virgin maidservant as opposed to one who has
had sex in order to, you know, attend to him, to go
ahead and like, I don't know, be a house slave. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, שפחה בעולה... shifcha beulah...
one minute, כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בין שפחה בתולה לשפחה בעולה kama
adam rotzeh liten bein shifcha betulah l’shifcha beulah לשמשה. l’shamshah. So שפחה
בעולה לשמשה מאי נפקא ליה מיניה? shifcha beulah l’shamshah mai nafkali minei?
So what difference does it make? If all this person is doing
is, I don't know, she's cooking in the kitchen, what does he
care whether she's a virgin or not? אלא בין שפחה בעולה לשפחה
שאינה בעולה להשיאה לעבדו. Ela bein shifcha beulah l’shifcha she’einah beulah l’hashiah
l’avdo.
No, he wants to buy this maidservant in order to marry her
off to his slave, and therefore his slave cares whether she's a
virgin or not. So therefore he'll pay a higher price for a
virgin. So the גמרא Gemara says ולאבדו מאי נפקא ליה מיניה? u’l’avdo
mai nafkali minei? So what does he care whether his slave wants,
you know, would rather, you know, marry a virgin or not? All
the master cares about is making babies. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, בעבד שיש לו לרבו קורת רוח הימנו, b’eved sheyesh lo l’rabo
korat ruach heimenu, it's a slave that the master likes and therefore
he wants to do the slave a favor. So if he wants
to do the slave a favor, he'll buy the slave a woman
who's a virgin as opposed to a slave woman who's not a
virgin. So once again we get this whole commodification of the woman.
Now of course you get this even by personal injury as well.
You ask about like a man's arm is broken. How much would
you pay in the slave market for a person with an arm
and without an arm and whatever? When the תורה Torah has to
and הלכה halacha. has to determine the dollar value for personal injury,
it does it based on the slave market because that's the only
model that it has of assigning a dollar value to a person.
Now for us it seems very, besides, you know, that it's objectifying,
which I mean, slavery was totally objectifying to human beings and now
that's being applied to us,
but in addition, of course, the question is like how is that
at all fair? I mean, does that at all approximate? I mean,
there are other payments, you know, pain and suffering and so on,
but it really
does not seem like it would at all approximate some type of
a dollar amount that somebody might feel would be actually fair compensation.
But that's the reality of this payment of the פגם. pegam, Now
תוספות Tosafot asks a question and תוספות Tosafot, says one minute. If
you like, it's one thing to say
somebody's arm was broken and so when you pay for the difference
about a slave with an arm and without an arm, essentially you're
also paying for like the loss of earnings because if a slave
with an arm could let's
say earn you $100,000 a year because he was a quarterback for
a football team or something and a slave without an arm could
only
earn $20,000 a year and you multiply that by the years of
productive labor of the slave and that would factor into the different
price of the slave. So to some degree it would approximate the
actual loss in terms of at least the loss of earnings. Okay,
but תוספות Tosafot says in this issue of a woman becoming a
non-virgin, the loss to the person, if you think about it, let's
say this person is of a very high social standing and she
was a virgin or whatever, so she would have gotten herself a
husband of a very high social standing as well. Now this is
a woman who is not a virgin, has been raped. She won't
be able like to maybe, you know, marry somebody of an upper
class. That's a huge loss. It's not just a loss about how
much difference it would make to marry a type of a woman
who was a virgin versus non-virgin to your slave, right? That's maybe
worth I don't know $100 to your slave or $1,000 or whatever,
but it does not necessarily reflect the loss to the person,
which might at least differ based on other factors as well. So
if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot כמה אדם רוצה ליתן
להשיאה לעבדו, Kama adam rotzeh liten l’hashiah l’avdo, תוספות Tosafot says תימה
דמאי שומא היא זו וכי אישה חשובה ממשפחה גדולה אינה נפסדת בפגמה
אלא שווה שפחה הנישאת לעבד? Teima d’mai shuma hi zu v’chi isha
chashuvah mimishpacha gedolah einah nifsedet b’fagma ela shaveh shifcha haniset l’eved? Is
that the only difference? Meaning even if acknowledging that there's already a
bizarre equation to the slave market, but at least the slave market
equation by other things takes into account other differences, like was this
person a high earner or not a high earner. That would be
reflected in the slave market price, but what this woman and what
her virginity meant to her is not reflected in the slave market
price. So the גמרא Gemara says ויש לומר v'yeish lomar דכל אשה
שמין לפי מה שהיא בענין זה d'chol isha shamin l'fi mah shehi
b'inyan zeh כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בדמי בתולה לבעולה להשיא לעבדו אשה
כזאת הנפגמת. kamah adam rotzeh litein bidmei betula l'be'ula l'hasi l'avdo isha
kazot hanifgemet. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot, says,
תוספות Tosafot basically says, well no, it would be the difference of
if you wanted to buy in the slave market a woman of
very high social standing, I don't know what she would be doing
being sold in the slave market, you know, and how much would
that difference be between בתולה and בעולה? be'ula?
For your עבד though.
But it would still be right for your עבד. I understand. So
it's, but anyway at least he puts the problem on the table.
Rabbi Dov you had a question before?
Yes, a couple of things. First of all, I don't understand really
why the תלמוד Talmud has to get involved with needing a different
פסוק, pasuk, as in the case of the father sells the daughter
you would think that he has transferred
his ריבונות ribonut from himself to the new master. You would need
a פסוק pasuk to say no that's not the case. That's not
exactly what the תלמוד Talmud does. Huh?
I don't understand.
Wait a minute, I have a daughter, I sell her to you,
she now has a new master. Right. So you would think that
I have given up my masterhood over my daughter.
You have.
So you need
a פסוק pasuk to say yes that's not the case. Wait a
minute, it's not the case?
I don't understand what you're saying. The פסוק pasuk told you that
after you sold her, when you sold her you don't get her
earnings. When it says מעשה בת לאביה, ma'aseh bat l'aviha, it means
how do you know you're entitled to her earnings when you haven't
sold her? From the fact that you can sell her and give
her earnings over to somebody else shows you that when you haven't
sold her you're entitled to her earnings. It's
not telling you you're entitled to her earnings after selling her. You're
not. The whole purpose you're selling her is that somebody else gets
her earnings.
Right, so here there's a, they quote a פסוק pasuk that corrects
for that, that even after you sell her the father still retains...
No, that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying. You misunderstood the
גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara is saying that because, that when the
father sells her the master gets her earnings. From this we learn
that when she isn't sold the father gets her earnings. Not that
he gets earnings after selling her. No, the whole point of selling
her was that the other master gets her earnings. Yes.
This slave market that we're talking about? Yes. Is it a Jewish
slave market or non-Jewish slave market?
Yeah, I mean a Jew what do you mean, I mean Jews
could be the buyers but the slaves being sold are the, are
non-Jews. Oh non-Jews.
Right, it's not a, because a Jewish slave is totally different.
Right, because here the whole point is to assign a dollar value
to a human being or to different values of human beings and
therefore it would only be the non-Jewish slave market where the whole
person is being sold, like a whole dollar value is assigned to
the person, whereas the Jewish slave market you're only buying the labor
for a certain number of years.
Okay, it's very, yeah, I mean it's a very disturbing מודל. model.
I mean the slave market in general is deeply disturbing. Now we're
just applying it to us. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
moving on. Okay, כל מקום שיש מכר אין קנס kol makom she'yesh
mecher ein knas we gotta keep them moving we're way behind. כל
מקום שיש מכר אין קנס וכל מקום שיש קנס אין מכר.
kol makom she'yesh mecher ein knas v'chol makom she'yesh
knas ein mecher. So this is the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that we quoted before. Where there is sale, meaning while she's
a, while she's a קטנה, ktana, because the father can only sell
her, he can marry her as a נערה, na'ara, but he can
only sell her as a קטנה. ktana. So when he can, when
there is sale up to the age of twelve, then there's no
קנס. knas קנס knas only begins at the, at the age of
twelve when she's a נערה. na'ara וכל מקום שיש קנס, v'chol makom
she'yesh knas, when there's קנס knas. when she's a נערה, na'ara, אין
מכר, ein mecher, he can't sell her. Again, as a נערה na'ara,
she could still be married off by the father but could not
be sold as a slave. Okay. קטנה יש לה מכר ואין לה
קנס נערה יש לה קנס ואין לה מכר. ktana yesh lah mecher
v'ein lah knas na'ara yesh lah knas v'ein lah mecher. It just
spells it out. An underage girl, a קטנה, ktana, minor, can be
sold but not, there's no קנס. knas And a נערה, na'ara a
girl in her youth whatever from twelve to twelve and a half,
there is קנס knas. she can't be sold as a slave. הבוגרת,
habogeret, once she is mature, twelve and a half, the whole ripe
age of twelve and a half, אין לה לא מכר ולא קנס,
ein lah lo mecher v'lo knas, cannot be sold nor is there
a קנס. knas אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, זו דברי רבי מאיר, zu divrei Rabbi Meir, these are the
words of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, but the
Sages say יש לה קנס במקום מכר, yesh lah knas bimkom mecher,
that קנס knas and מכר mecher can overlap, that there is קנס
knas. even when she's a קטנה. ktana. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, קטנה מבת יום אחד ועד שתביא שתי שערות, ktana
mibat yom echad v'ad shetavi shtei se'arot, a קטנה ktana from day
one until she has two pubic hairs, until she's a נערה, na'arah,
יש לה מכר ואין לה קנס, yesh lah mecher v'ein lah knas,
can be sold but there's no קנס. knas No קנס knas for
קטנה. ktana. משתביא שתי שערות, mishetavi shtei se'arot, once she has the
two pubic hairs, עד שתבגר, ad shetivgare, until she becomes mature, יש
לה קנס ואין לה מכר. yesh lah knas v'ein lah mecher. Then
she's a נערה na'arah. and there's a קנס knas but there's no
sale. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, shehaya Rabbi Meir omer, because he
used to say כל מקום שיש מכר אין קנס וכל מקום שיש
קנס אין מכר. kol makom she'yesh mecher ein knas v'chol makom she'yesh
knas ein mecher. When there's one there's not the other. וחכמים אומרים,
v'Chachamim omrim, and the Sages say, קטנה מבת ג' שנים ויום אחד,
ktana mibat shalosh shanim v'yom echad, from three years from one from
one day to three years there's only מכר, mecher, there's no קנס
knas. because it's not considered an act of sex. From three years
until she becomes a בוגרת, bogeret, through her בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah
through six months later until she becomes a בוגרת. bogeret. So starting
at those three years once it's an act of sex and she's
even though she's a קטנה, ktana, מבת ג' שנים ויום אחד ועד
שתבגר יש לה קנס. mibat shalosh shanim v'yom echad v'ad shetivgare yesh
lah knas. She has קנס. knas So there's קנס knas? even for
קטנה. ktana. So the גמרא Gemara says, קנס אין מכר לא? knas
in mecher lo? What, only קנס? knas So the גמרא Gemara says,
אימא אף קנס במקום מכר. eima af knas bimkom mecher. No, clearly,
meaning sale. goes from birth till twelve.
קנס knas can even exist at times when there are sale, קנס
knas. is even when she's a קטנה ktanah from three years and
one day all the way until she's a בוגרת. bogeret. Okay, so
this could have been
set up a bit more clearly, I mean, fine. אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Meir? What's
the reason of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? אמר קרא, Amar kra, ולא
תהיה לאשה. v'lo tihiyeh l'ishah. It says by the case by rape,
to him she shall be for a wife. ומהוה עצמה קא משתעי.
v'mehaveh atzmah ka mishta'ei.
It's talking about a woman that can marry herself. Although the father
can marry off the daughter against her will since she's a נערה,
na'arah. the woman herself can also accept the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
So she can be part of the process of marrying herself as
a נערה. na'arah, So since it uses the verb in reference to
her, ולא תהיה לאשה, v'lo tihiyeh l'ishah, to him she should be,
it doesn't say to him the father should marry her off, it
seems that we're talking about a נערה. na'arah Okay. I mean the
תורה Torah already says נערה, na'arah but the way we know to
say only נערה na'arah not קטנה ktanah is the repetition here of
this פסוק pasuk which indicates that she is, that she's already halachically
an adult. ורבנן? V'rabbanan? And the rabbis, what would the rabbis say
back? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Rish Lakish, אמר קרא, amar kra, נערה
na'arah, here should be written, here it should appear in the גמרא
Gemara without the ה. hei.
Where does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir learn from that ולא תהיה לאשה?
v'lo tihiyeh l'ishah? That she's a נערה na'arah. because she's able to
marry herself. I mean the תורה Torah already says נערה, na'arah but
the repetition presumably says only a נערה. na'arah, Now the verse actually
when it says נערה na'arah. by the case of rape, writes it
without the letter ה. hei. Okay, and therefore, the writing without the
letter ה hei indicates for the חכמים chachamim that she's not, even
when she's not a full נערה, na'arah. even when she's a קטנה.
ktanah. Okay. Is it, what is it? What, is it what obvious?
Oh, it's that you're being facetious? I don't know, it's an interesting
point that it's not written with a ה. hei. I mean, we
could just put it down to spelling differences, but the גמרא Gemara
wants to learn everything from every hint. So the lack of the
ה hei says she's not a full נערה. na'arah, אפילו קטנה במשמע.
afilu ktanah bemashma. So שמע רב פפא בריה דרב חנן מבי כלוחית.
shama Rav Papa breih de'Rav Chanan mi-bei Kluchis. So this רב פפא
Rav Papa heard this and אזל אמר קמיה דרב שימי בר אשי
azal amar kamei de'Rav Shimi bar Ashi and he told this דרשה
drasha to רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi that without
the ה hei it implies even a קטנה. ktanah. אמר amar ליה,
he said to him, אתון אהא מתניתו לה. atun aha matnitu lah.
You teach that idea that without the ה hei it implies a
קטנה ktanah on this discussion about the קנס. knas אנן אהא מתנינא
לה. Anan aha matnina lah. We teach it on the following discussion.
אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Rish Lakish, המוציא שם רע אקטנה פטור. hamotzi
shem ra a-ktanah patur. That there's another place the תורה Tora talks
about special payments which we're going to get to in the next
פרק. perek. About a נערה. na'arah. About the man who claims that
in the next morning, all about this issue about virginity and the
נערה, na'arah the man who claims
the next morning that his wife wasn't a בתולה and that she
had committed adultery, you run that whole story about מוציא שם רע
motzi shem ra and then stoning her or he has to pay
a fine, etc. So would that apply to a קטנה? ktanah? So
ריש לקיש Rish Lakish says no, that special פרשה parsha of מוציא
שם רע motzi shem ra applies only to a נערה. na'arah. Even
the חכמים chachamim who say that the קנס knas, the fifty applies
to a קטנה ktanah would agree that the הלכות halachot of מוציא
שם רע motzi shem ra of the guy sort of spreading ill
report or whatever on his wife, that's only a נערה na'arah דוקא.
davka. How do you know that? המוציא שם רע אקטנה פטור. Hamotzi
shem ra a-ktanah patur. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the verse says, ונתנו לאבי הנערה,
v'natnu l'avi hana'arah, pay to the father of the נערה. na'arah נערה
מלא דיבר הכתוב. Na'arah malei diber hakatuv. There the word נערה na'arah
is spelled full. It's spelled with the ה. hei. So it so
that implicitly tells you the reason the rabbis know
that
the case, our case of the קנס, knas is even a קטנה,
ktanah, is because it's spelled without the ה. hei. Whereas they don't
always say נערה na'arah. means קטנה. ktanah. In the case of מוציא
שם רע motzi shem ra where נערה na'arah. is spelled with the
ה, hei, they say it means only really a נערה. na'arah, Okay.
So that's actually a nice consistent
דרשה. drasha.
Wait, though, in that whole
פסוק, pasuk, in that whole passage?
Alright, but at least it says the word נערה.
na'arah, Oh, it's actually missing a ה.
hei. Fine, okay. Fine, but at least it says it once. מתקיף
לה רב אדא בר אהבה. Matkif lah Rav Adda bar Ahava. So
רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava asks on this. טעמא
דכתב רחמנא נערה. Ta'ama de'ktav Rachmana na'arah. The reason you're saying the
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra is only a נערה, na'arah, a
real נערה, is because it's with a ה. hei. הא לאו הכי
הוה אמינא אפילו קטנה. Ha lav hachi havah amina afilu ktanah. Had
it not been the extra ה hei I would have said even
if she's a minor. והכתיב, V'haktiv, ואם אמת היה הדבר הזה לא
נמצאו בתולים לנערה, v'im emet hayah hadavar hazeh lo nimtze'u betulim lana'arah,
that if it was true that she was not a virgin and
therefore assumed to have committed adultery, והוציאו את הנערה פתח בית אביה,
v'hotzi'u et hana'arah petach beit aviha, they shall take this the young
girl out to the door of the father's house, וסקלוה, v'sakluha, and
stone her. So clearly, if they're stoning the woman for having committed
adultery, she is an adult. If she were a minor, she would
not be punished. וקטנה לאו בת עונשין היא. V'ktanah lav bat onshin
hi.
And a minor is not subject to punishment. So he's not disagreeing
with the הלכה. halakhah You're right, מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra
clearly the girl is a נערה, not a קטנה, ktanah, because the
תורה Tora speaks about the possibility that if she committed adultery, she'll
be executed. But you don't need the extra ה hei to tell
you that. You just know it from the fact that it's assuming
that she's an adult because it talks about her punishment if she
committed adultery. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay fine, אלא הכא נמי,
ela hacha nami, you're right. We didn't learn it out from the
ה. hei. We learned out that מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra
she was an adult from the fact that the תורה Tora says
that she would be executed. But now that we know she's an
adult in the case of מוציא שם רע, motzi shem ra, now
it can tell you how to read the significance of the presence
or the absence of the letter ה. Heh. So we don't start
with this idea that the letter ה Heh makes a difference. We
start with the idea that it's clear there she's an adult. And
then we say ah she's an adult? Oh wait a minute and
here there is a ה Heh and there there is not a
ה. Heh. Maybe that tells you whether the person is an adult
or not. אלא כאן נערה, Ella kan na'arah, here we know she's
an adult, הכא מקום שנאמר נער, hecha makom shene'emar naar, if it
didn't have the ה, Heh, we would say אפילו קטנה במשמע, afillu
ketannah bemashma, even a minor and that's how we know that by
the קנס knas according to the חכמים, Chachamim, it's even if she's
a קטנה. ketannah. Okay so that's something that we've already known, this
issue about the difference of רב מאיר Rav Meir and the חכמים
Chachamim whether it applies to a קטנה. ketannah. Now we're finally up
to today's דף, daf. top of מ"א
ע"א. Mem Aleph Amud Aleph. Okay, now we get to these issues
about בושת and פגם that we are
what do you call it that we've established that there's these different
payments. There's the קנס knas, which is a fixed amount, which is
being called a קנס, knas a fine, although we discussed yesterday that
it's really not so much of a fine as it's because the
father is not going to get the מהר, mohar, the bride price
he normally would've gotten and that's why he's getting this right and
we discussed yesterday the whole idea that the normal bride price of
fifty שקל was there to protect the became a type of a
pseudo כתובה ketubah and was there to protect the woman's interest and
then it got later moved to the back of the marriage and
also was there to ensure that there was not over hasty divorce
and that was the whole issue yesterday about whether there is a
כתובה ketubah in the cases of אונס ומפתה. ones u-mefatteh. But anyway,
so that from that perspective you could've looked at the fifty as
not so much of a fine but that as a compensating the
father because he's not going to get the bride price he normally
would've gotten. But the גמרא Gemara does not look at it that
way, the משנה, Mishnah the משנה Mishnah looks at it as a
fine as opposed to the payments for injury for בושת and פגם,
those are payments of actual compensation of called ממון, mamon, those are
monetary payments, not payments of not fines. Why does that matter? For
the following reason. Let's look at our משנה Mishna what the different
הלכה halacha is between a monetary fine and monetary payment. האומר פיתיתי
את בתו של פלוני, Ha-omer pititi et bitto shel peloni, somebody says
that I seduced this man's daughter, so
and therefore I'm liable for all the payments, משלם בושת ופגם על
פי עצמו, meshalem boshet u-pegam al pi atzmo, he pays for the
embarrassment and the injury based on his own
testimony, ואין משלם קנס, ve-ein meshalem knas, but he does not pay
for a fine and this is a principle that fines can only
be imposed by the court and only be imposed they don't exist
they're not like objective debts, they're they're fine the same like it's
it's a punishment imposed by the court and it can only be
imposed if there's objective testimony, if there's external witnesses. Based on a
person's own testifying cannot obligate himself in a fine. It even goes
further than that that some that that the testifying even will it
will exempt you from a fine later on even if witnesses come
and say you've done it. But before we even worry about your
your admission exempting you, certainly it does not obligate you. Okay so
if the person therefore confesses he only pays the monetary payments, the
ones that are seen as a type of compensation and not the
ones that are seen as a monetary punishment, the ones that are
a fine.
משלם בושת ופגם על פי עצמו ואין משלם קנס. meshalem boshet u-pegam
al pi atzmo ve-ein meshalem knas. האומר גנבתי Ha-omer ganavti and now
we're going to get off from the from our specific issue of
קנס knas. and discuss other cases of קנס. knas, Somebody that says
that I burgled,
משלם את הקרן meshalem et ha-keren and he confesses it, he pays
the principal על פי עצמו al pi atzmo based on his own
testimony, ואין משלם תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, ve-ein meshalem tashlumei kefel
ve-tashlumei arba'ah va-chamishah, but he does not pay the double and the
four and the five because those are fines and that you don't
pay on your own testimony. המית שורי את פלוני, Hamit shori et
peloni, my ox gored a certain person, או שורו של פלוני, o
shoro shel peloni, or gored his ox, הרי זה משלם על פי
עצמו, harei zeh meshalem al pi atzmo, then he pays, he pays
because and it's not just gored it meant killed somebody, he pays
because those are compensation. Now the idea that there's compensation for killing
somebody, if your ox kills somebody that no well we're not talking
about עבד, that would be a fine. This is compensation, that would
be a כופר, kofer, you know, a כופר kofer which is like
a ransom. So there's a question whether כופר kofer is seen as
the to atone for my soul because it was my ox that
gored it and I'm basically therefore paying the value of myself and
therefore it's not really a type of a תשלומין, tashlumin, is whether
is it a קנס, knas. how to understand it, that's one thing.
But this משנה Mishna presumably we understand that when my ox if
an ox gored and killed somebody you're paying for the dead person
and their value and somehow again use the slave market and you
give a dollar value to the person's life. Okay and therefore that's
a type of a תשלומין tashlumin not a type of a קנס.
knas. So if you do that payment or if it gored another
ox you do it based on your own testimony. But המית שורי
עבדו של פלוני, Hamit shori avdo shel peloni, if my ox gored
somebody's slave, then that's now that we would say is also a
compensation for the lost slave, but here the משנה Mishna makes a
חידוש. chiddush. How do you know whether something is a fine or
a compensation? Okay and it says if something is a fixed amount
and never changes based on circumstances then it can't be a compensation
because compensation always has to do with values and circumstances. So if
it's always
fifty שקל. But the משנה Mishna assumes not that way. Nope. If
it's a fixed amount, it's not a compensation. It's a fine. אין
משלמים על פי עצמו. Ain m'shalmim al pi atzmo. זה הכלל, Zeh
haklal, so you don't pay when you testify admit that your ox
gored somebody's slave. This is the rule. כל המשלם יתר על מה
שהזיק אין משלם על פי עצמו. Kol ham'shalem yeter al mah she'hizik
ain m'shalem al pi atzmo. If you're ever going to wind up
paying more than the actual damages, you don't do it based on
your own testimony. Now I want to say something because what I
actually said a minute ago, which is if it's fixed, it's considered
a fine, is not exactly what the משנה Mishna said. The משנה
Mishna. says if you pay more. You could imagine somebody that would
let's say always pay less. Let's say for example, we lived in
a reality that all slaves were worth at least 50 שקל, 50
שקל and up. And the תורה Tora said you always pay 30
שקל. So I might not consider it a fine. I might just
say that the תורה Torah puts a ceiling to your payment, right?
The תורה Torah. says you'll always pay a partial compensation fixed at
30 שקל. So if you sometimes pay less than the damages, it
doesn't prove that it's a fine. It could just be saying you'll
pay partial damages. But if there be scenarios you pay more, if
a certain slave was worth only 10 שקל and you're going to
pay 30, so if the תורה Torah. will have you at times
pay more, then clearly it's a fine. Anything more than the actual
damages, so since sometimes slaves are worth less than 30 שקל and
you will still pay 30 שקל shows that we should look at
this, the whole thing here as a קנס. knas Okay, yes?
Doesn't this set up a situation where a person would want to
admit to something maybe they didn't do it? Yes.
So in our משנה Mishna you don't know that admitting actually gets
you off the hook. You just know that admitting to a קנס
knas doesn't obligate you. In theory, witnesses could come later and obligate
you. It's a different principle that when you admit to something, you
actually get exempt even if witnesses come later and then there are
some limits to when we say that principle. Okay, but but right?
All our משנה Mishnah said is that your own admission doesn't doesn't
obligate you. So there's no incentive to admit according to our משנה.
Mishnah, Something that gets you off the hook of the additional compensation?
It didn't say that. Our משנה Mishnah just says you don't obligate
yourself based on your own admission. It didn't say, now you're right,
there's another principle that, again, there's a question about how much is
it universal, the גמרא Gemara assumes it's universal, but it's not black
and white certainly in these משניות Mishnayot that your admission gets you
off the hook. It just says your admission doesn't obligate you. All
right.
So doesn't obligate you means sufficient in and of itself.
Sufficient in itself, right, to obligate you. But it is true that
there's other הלכות Halachot that your admission actually can get you off
the hook even if witnesses come later and when we get to
that, we can discuss that and that is a surprising, right? Because
then there's an incentive to admit, but the but the attitude of
the גמרא Gemara might be sure, good, there's an incentive to admit
because the purpose of this is actually to get you to confess
and whatever, maybe that's part of the function it's supposed to serve.
But in the English, I was responding to the English, it just
says but does not pay the fine.
Well, it's true, it does not pay based on the admission itself.
It doesn't it doesn't tell you what would be the consequence if
there were, it means all we have is your admission. Your admission
is enough to make you pay one category, but not enough others.
מודה בקנס פטור.
Modeh b'knas
patur. Okay.
All right. So let's keep on going. וליתני, U'litni, so you might
have said so why now we've been talking about rape, rape, rape,
why now do we switch to the case of seduction? וליתני אנסתי,
U'litni anasti,
why doesn't it give the case that a guy says I raped
this woman and therefore he pays the the monetary payments but not
the fine? אמר רבא לא מבעיא קאמר, Amar Rava lo mibaya ka'amar,
it goes without saying. לא מבעיא אנסתי, Lo mibaya anasti,
certainly if he says he raped this woman, דלא פגים לה, d'lo
pagim lah, he is not claiming that she's of ill repute, right?
He's the one that rapes her. Again, as we know, in ancient
societies, if a woman was raped, it didn't matter, she was like
she was the one that was shamed. But the גמרא Gemara is
at least acknowledging that it doesn't mean that she did anything wrong.
So he's saying he's the one that did this terrible act. So
in that case, דלא פגים לה דמשלם בושת ופגם על פי עצמו,
d'lo pagim lah d'm'shalem boshet uf'gam al pi atzmo, so he's going
to pay it based on his own admission. אבל פיתיתי, Aval pititi,
but if he says that I seduced this woman, so basically he's
also saying something about her, he's saying that she's loose, that she's
he's he's spreading ill repute about her. דקפגים לה, D'kapagim lah, so
he's spreading ill repute about her, אימא לא משלם על פי עצמו,
eima lo m'shalem al pi atzmo, so maybe we won't let him
pay, right? It's an interesting point. He says I seduced this woman
and here I'm going to pay for the fine. Maybe we should
refuse to accept the money or allow him to pay it because
by allowing him to pay it, we are allowing him to basically
spread ill repute about this other woman. If he says that she
did this consensual act of sex with him. So the גמרא Gemara.
says, so in that case, אימא לא משלם על פי עצמו, eima
lo m'shalem al pi atzmo, maybe we don't let him pay, maybe
he's lying, maybe it's all part of a whole scheme to make
her look bad or something. Who knows what it is? But we
can't, you know, without objective testimony, we maybe we shouldn't accept the
money. קמ"ל Kamashma lan that we do,
that maybe we're able to bracket whatever reason he gave and says
he wants to pay the money, he'll pay the money. Okay, and
we don't have to be concerned about the explanation that he gave
for why why he's paying it. מתניתין לא כי האי תנא, Masnisin
lo ki hai tanna, but it raises an interesting question, and now
we're gonna say that there's actually a תנא tanna that disagrees. Our
משנה Mishnah is not like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: baraita: רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rebbi Shimon, אף פותה שבפגם
אינו משלם על פי עצמו. Af poteh she-be-pgam eino meshalem al pi
atzmo. In the case of seduction, he is not believed, and maybe
even in the case of rape, but certainly in the case of
seduction, he is not believed to pay even the payments of בושת
ופגם, boshes u-pgam, the monetary payments. He pays nothing. If you have
witnesses he pays, but not based on his own admission. לא כל
הימנו שיפגום בתו של פלוני. Lo kol heimeninu she-yifgom bito shel ploni.
We don't believe him that he that his to allow him to
sort of, you know, to spread to injure, meaning you know, through
his words, to spread ill repute about this man's daughter. Okay, so
therefore we would we don't accept. Now the interesting question is is
he saying that only by seduction or, as we know, you know,
in as again in some like, you know, Middle Eastern societies even
till today, even if a woman is raped, she's the one who
is shamed and she's the one who's an embarrassment and looks bad.
So maybe we wouldn't even accept his admission even in the case
of rape because anytime a man says that whether he seduced or
raped a woman, the reality is that it winds up hurting the
woman. Okay, so maybe we shouldn't. But certainly in the case of
seduction, he says we don't accept his testimony even to make him
pay because that will just because that eventually will do more harm
to her than than, you know, than of than than than if
we accepted the money than if we didn't accept the money, excuse
me.
But we believe it like if like bragging aside like, you know,
the witnesses say okay whatever the whatever the precipitating factors of this
encounter let's say she gets injured otherwise through this. Right. You don't
pay for that either? You know not because of an act like
he breaks her arm during this thing if it's a violent rape.
Right. They wouldn't have to pay in the admission?
Yeah, I don't know. That's a good question. You know because how
much do we package it all together? I don't know. So could
we could we separate it? We say we believe he broke her
arm, we don't believe anything else? Maybe. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, שיפגום בתו של פלוני. She-yifgom bito shel ploni. אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי: Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye: ניחא לה לדידה מאי?
Nicha lah le-didah mai?
Let's say she says, no, you know what? I don't care whatever
story he's telling me, I want that money and I think we
should accept the money. Maybe she doesn't admit she did it or
not, but she says I'm happy to have us take his money.
So what do we say? So the גמרא Gemara says, דילמא לא
ניחא ליה לאבוה. Dilma lo nicha lei le-avuhah. Okay, but maybe it's
not the father isn't okay with it. You know, and maybe the
father has a right not to be embarrassed and so on. You
know, part of these payments go to the father anyway or not
part the payments do go to the father.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine. ניחא ליה לאבוה מאי? Nicha lei
le-avuhah mai? Let's say the father says I'll take the money. Okay,
and she says I'll take the money. So do we have to
protect their interest that they shouldn't be shamed by this according to
this approach if they're not bothered by that? So the גמרא Gemara
says, דילמא לא ניחא להו לבני משפחה. Dilma lo nicha lehu li-vnei
mishpacha. No, we do. Even though the maybe the rest of the
family, you know, will be shamed as a result. So even though
the rest of the family isn't entitled to the money, okay, maybe
we as the בית דין beis din have to sort of bring
our sort of, you know, protect society and protect the families and
therefore we use that sort of policy considerations to determine whether we
should accept this testimony. It's quite interesting. Again, we've had other cases
before where policy and הלכה halacha intersect. Right, הלכתית halachically somebody admits
to a fine, they're believed and they owe the money. Right, that's
הלכה halacha pure and simple. If I admit that I owe you
a thousand dollars, then that's binding on me and I have to
the court makes me pay a thousand dollars. But here, in order
to protect the interests of the family even if the immediate parties,
the father and the daughter, are okay with it, maybe we should
refuse to accept your testimony. Let's see what it says. So ניחא
להו לבני משפחה מאי? Nicha lehu li-vnei mishpacha mai? Let's say the
family, all the family says they're okay with it. No. אי אפשר
דליכא חד במדינת הים דלא ניחא ליה. Ee efshar de-leika chad bi-mdinas
hayam de-lo nicha lei. Who knows? Maybe there's one family member in
China that would not want it. So therefore we have to protect
the interests of the family even where, you know.
Where what about אביה?
aviah? Well
no, I mean the payment might be אביה, aviah, but this is
a different question. This is a question about allowing somebody to spread
ill repute to and which would be which would be reinforced right,
which would be reinforced by maybe he didn't violate her, he's making
the whole thing up. So do we allow somebody to to spread
this to spread this rumor which will get reinforced by our accepting
of the money or is it our jobs as sort of to
protect society and protect innocent people to protect, you know, people that
will indirectly be hurt by this type of a claim? Okay, so
it's an interesting question. Of course, you could imagine other scenarios having
nothing to do with rape where I admit to something which indirectly
reinforces certain bad impressions of other people and so on. Right, how
much do we allow these types of, you know, policy considerations to
interfere with the natural running of the court? Yes.
And if there are really witnesses to these things, if she says
he seduced me and he says yes I seduced her, we're not
going to accept that? Is that what we're saying?
I'm sorry hold on a second. You mean you mean what happens
if so so meaning I think some somebody raises this question about
what happens if she like if she initiates the proceedings. Like maybe
this is a little bit different because he's the one that came
forward. Right, if she's the one that actually like initiates the
proceedings. What if he initiates? What if he initiates? She says, yes,
you know what, I'm— Right. Okay. So that's what I said, right.
One minute. Let me read it inside.
Right,
so even if the—even
if it's
acceptable—No, acceptable to take the money. Let's say they actually admit that
it happened. Right. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot he
says, there's a difference between saying, okay, we'll take the money.
תוספות says two lines down in the narrow lines, I won't get
into the technical question he's asking, but he says, היינו דמשום דקדם
תבעו האב תחילה, Hainu d'mishum d'kadam tva'u ha-av techila, אין צריך לומר
לאו כל הימנו. ein tzarich lomar lav kol heimenu.
So תוספות basically says when the father, maybe the daughter as well,
is the one that basically sues him and says, you seduced my
daughter, you seduced me, you owe me this, then it's different. Then
basically they're themselves saying that it happened and they're the ones putting
it forward and therefore obviously then he would have to pay even
according to רב שמעון's Rav Shimon approach here if he admitted to
it. So what happens if he said it and then they afterwards
admitted it happened? Maybe that would be different also. Okay. Yes.
Isn't there a justification from the תורה Torah that this has to
do with the whole בני משפחה? bnei mishpacha?
It seems that only people—Again, Michael, we're not talking about the actual
damage itself that the בני משפחה bnei mishpacha are embarrassed. We're talking
about, we're talking about, we're talking about that it didn't happen and
we're just concerned about the claim and how the claim reflects on
them. It's not a payment in the תורה. Torah It's our responsibility
to protect society and protect innocent people from having bad things said
about them. It has nothing to do with the payments in the
תורה. Torah Okay. You say this guy said bad things, it'll reflect
poorly on the family. Do we allow him to back that up
through some type of collecting money and hurt the reputation of the
family? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, האומר גנבתי
משלם את הקרן. ha'omer ganavti m'shalem et hakeren. Now we get to
a classic debate in the גמרא. Gemara Let's see if we can
at least get to the bottom of the דף.
איתמר, Itmar, it was taught, פלגא ניזקא, palga nizka, when my ox
gores another ox and it has a non-habitual gorer, it's a תם,
tam, it pays half damages. Okay, so here's an interesting question. Is
the half damages a fine or is it partial compensation? Is it
קנס Knas. or is it ממון? mamon? And notice here, as I
mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah. it's never more than the damages. It's
always less. So if it's always less, it's reasonable to assume it's
partial compensation, not a fine, even though it's not the full amount.
So what's the story? פלגא ניזקא, palga nizka, half damages. רב פפא
Rav Papa אמר פלגא ניזקא ממונא, palga nizka mamona, that is monetary,
it's compensation, half compensation. רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua אמר פלגא ניזקא קנסא, palga nizka knasa, it's a fine.
רב פפא Rav Papa אמר פלגא ניזקא ממונא, palga nizka mamona, it's
compensation. קסבר סתם שוורים לאו
בחזקת שימור קיימי,
kasavar stam shvarim lav b'chezkas
shimur kaymi, because he feels that even unhabitual oxen cannot be assumed
to naturally be protected against going out and goring. Okay, you can't
assume that they're self-protected. You have responsibility to watch even your tame
oxen. ובדין הוא, ub'din hu, and therefore if it goes and gores
somebody or somebody's ox, ובדין הוא דמשלם כוליה, ub'din hu d'mshalem kulei,
you really should pay full. רחמנא הוא דחס עליה, Rachmana hu d'chas
alei, but the תורה Torah had רחמנות rachmanus on you, דאכתי לאו
אייעדו, d'achti lav i'adu, the ox hasn't been warned. So meaning you're
negligent, but you're only barely on this side of the line of
negligence. And therefore the תורה gives you a break the first three
times. So basically, you should be paying full compensation. You only pay
half because the תורה went easy on you. But clearly it's compensation.
It's half compensation because you're on this side of the negligence line.
Okay. There's another reason why
the
victim suffers by only getting half compensation for their actual losses because
they have the benefit of the same law. Right. Exactly.
Okay. ובדין הוא—yes, that's true, that there's always a tradeoff between the
perpetrator and the victim. Okay. דאכתי לאו אייעדו. רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua אמר פלגא ניזקא קנסא. palga nizka
knasa. No, it's a fine. קסבר סתם שוורים בחזקת שימור קיימי. kasavar
stam shvarim b'chezkas shimur kaymi. Before it's become habitual, you can assume
that your ox will be protected against going out and goring. You
really don't have a real responsibility to watch it. ובדין הוא דלא
לשלם כלל, ub'din hu d'lo l'shalem klal, and therefore technically you shouldn't
have to pay it all. You were not negligent. But you weren't
negligent, so what? Michael, you learn בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, if you're
not negligent, you're not liable. Okay, so you weren't negligent by not
watching your ox. רחמנא הוא דקנסיה, Rachmana hu d'kansei, but the תורה
fined you. Why? כי היכי דנינטריה לתוריה, ki heichi d'nintrei l'torei, that
you should be more careful and watch your ox. Meaning,
the best way to understand it is they're arguing of exactly which
side of the line of negligence you fall. Do you just fall
over the line of negligence or just under? So one approach is
you just fall over but you're barely negligent, so okay, technically you
should pay full, but since you're barely negligent, you pay half, but
it's still compensation. The other says you fall just under the line
of negligence, so technically you should be totally off the hook. But
we really would like you to be a little bit more careful,
okay? And therefore we're going to make you pay half even though
you shouldn't be paying anything to encourage you to be more careful.
So that's the— And
at least the victim gets something, but not because we're claiming you're
negligent. Technically you're not negligent. So that's the question, whether to look
at it as a fine or look at it as compensation. קנס.
Knas. קנס. knas Right. Well, no, strict liability means with no negligence
you're חייב. chayav. When your animals go and gore, it's only due
to negligence. But the question is, what do you deal with some
case that falls right on the line? You need negligence, what if
it falls right on the line? And which side of the line?
And that's what's being debated.
Okay. Is this the primary location of this debate here in?
No, it also exists in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Yeah, but it
but here's one of the locations. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, we'll skip the סימן, siman, which is a way of
of of knowing what are the cases that are going to be
looked at. תנן. Tnan. הניזק והמזיק בתשלומין. Ha'nizak ve'hamazik betashlumin.
We have a משנה in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that says in
a case that in a case of a שור תם, shor tam,
the both the damagee and the damager share the cost of the
damages, right? Because you split the cost of the because you only
pay half. בשלמא למאן דאמר פלגא ניזקא ממונא, Bishlama leman d'amar palga
nizka mamona, if you say half damages is compensation, היינו דשייך ניזק
בתשלומין, hainu d'shaich nizak betashlumin,
that's what it means that the damagee pays for half because he
should be getting full compensation, but he had to pay as it
were for half. He only he only gets half when he should
be getting full. אלא למאן דאמר פלגא ניזקא קנסא, Ella leman d'amar
palga nizka knasa, but if it's a fine, השתא דלאו דידיה קשקיל,
hasht d'lav didei ka'shakil,
the half that the damagee is getting, he doesn't really deserve because
the damager wasn't negligent. So he's already getting money he doesn't deserve.
ותשלומין איתא, Vetashlumin itta, so what does it need to say that
he shares in the cost of the of the loss? Meaning in
anything he's getting money. Now, of course you could say, at the
end of the day his ox is dead. Okay, but nevertheless and
he's paying
for not having an he's out an animal.
But he should be out the whole animal. Okay, so in principle
he's not entitled to anything and he's getting half. How can you
frame that as he's sharing in the cost? Okay, because if anything
he's lucky to be getting half. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says,
so the גמרא Gemara says... okay, לא נצרכא אלא לפחת
נבילה.
lo nitzrecha ella
l'pchat neveila. No,
this is taught for the הלכה halakha of the deprecation of the
value of the of the carcass of the animal. Depreciation, thank you.
Deprecation means something else. פחת נבילה, Pchat neveila, so meaning that if
the carcass devalues, you pay half of the cost of the difference
between the live animal and the dead one. And then the damagee,
the ניזק, nizak, takes the carcass and if it depreciates in the
you know, you know, in the over the next few days and
weeks or whatever, he suffers the full loss of that depreciation. Okay.
So therefore, that's what it says that he's included in the loss
because he's going to suffer the full loss of the depreciation of
the carcass and that won't have to be paid by the owner
of the ox. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, פחת נבילה תנינא,
pchat neveila tninah,
we've already taught that. תשלומי נזק, Tashlumei nezek, the משנה says that
you pay the payments of נזק nezek and somehow from that strange
articulation we learn the principle מלמד שבעלים מטפלין בנבילה, melamed she'ba'alim metaplim
bi'neveila, that the owners actually have to deal with the carcass and
if it depreciates it's their loss. So the גמרא Gemara says, חדא
בתם וחדא במועד וצריכא. chada bitam vechada bemo'ad vetzricha. No, it tells
you twice: once by a habitual gorer that the owners of the
dead animal deal with the carcass and once by a non-habitual, and
you need both. דאי אשמעינן תם משום דאכתי לא ועיד, D'i ashmi'inan
tam mishum d'ati lo ya'id,
so the guy's ox is not habitual, so he should be not
have to pay as much, so you the owner have to deal
with the depreciation of the carcass. אבל מועד דועיד, Aval mo'ad d'ya'id,
but the מועד mo'ad where he was warned, אימא לא, eima lo,
maybe the owner of the gorer should partly share in the depreciation.
ואי אשמעינן מועד, V'i ashmi'inan mo'ad, had you told me about the
case of מועד, mo'ad, משום דקמשלם כולא, mishum d'kameshallem kulla, he's already
paying the full amount, so he shouldn't have to also pay for
the loss of the for the depreciation. אבל תם, Aval tam, but
I might say by the
non-habitual, אימא לא, eima lo, since he's only paying half maybe also
he has to share in the depreciation, צריכא, tzricha, so it tells
you in neither case he shares. Fine. Anyway, bottom line is that
the language that they both share in the cost seems to reflect
the idea that it is partial compensation, but the גמרא gets out
of it. Let's do one other case, turn the page at least.
תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here. מה בין תם למועד, Ma
bein tam le'mo'ad,
what's the difference between a habitual and non-habitual? שהתם משלם חצי נזק,
She'hatam meshallem chatzi nezek,
the תם tam pays half damages, מגופו, migufo, and it also comes
out of the body of the gorer itself. You will never have
to pay more than the cost of the goring animal. Okay, so
if my... right, if my hundred dollar ox gores your thousand dollar
ox, okay, I'm not going to pay you five hundred dollars. I'm
going to give you my hundred dollar ox and I'm going to
be done with it. Okay, there's even a question about how much
you actually become an immediate owner in my ox. Okay, but the
limit of the payment can only be collected from the animal of
the gorer itself.
ומועד, U'mo'ad, but the case of a habitual gorer, משלם נזק שלם,
meshallem nezek shalem, it's full damages, מן העלייה, min ha'aliya, from the
best of the property, with no
limit. ולא קתני, V'lo k'tani, and it doesn't give as a difference,
שהתם אינו משלם על פי עצמו, she'hatam eino meshallem al pi atzmo,
that the תם tam does not pay through self-admission, ומועד משלם על
פי עצמו u'mo'ad meshallem al pi atzmo and the מועד mo'ad does.
So again that would seem to indicate that they're both תשלומין, tashlumin,
they're both money, they're both compensation, right? Because if one was a
fine, there are other differences that need to be pointed out. So
this is another evidence that it's תשלומין tashlumin and not a fine.
Is that clear? Because if it was a fine we have the
differences of our משנה. But says תנא ושייר. tana veshayer. No, there
is that difference about fine and תשלומין, tashlumin, but it's not a
complete list, it's an abbreviated list. The גמרא says מאי שייר דהאי
שייר? mai shayer de-hai shayer? You don't just leave one thing off
the list. So if it's not a full list, what else was
not on the list? ושייר חצי כופר. veshayer chatzi kofer. It left
off half of כופר. kofer. If an ox gores, a non-habitual ox
gores a person and kills the person, do you when it's habitual,
you pay כופר, kofer, the full amount. When it's non-habitual, do you
pay חצי כופר chatzi kofer of killing a person or not? So
that's debated in the גמרא. Okay, so the גמרא says that also
would be was left off, that should also have been put there
as a difference and it wasn't, so it's not a complete list
of differences. Okay.
One minute.
No, so the point being, by the way, let me be clear,
that when it says חצי כופר chatzi kofer is a difference, it
doesn't mean that the מועד muad pays full כופר kofer and the
תם tam pays half כופר. kofer. That would be the exact difference
it said of full and half. The הלכה actually is that a
תם tam doesn't pay, doesn't pay anything if it kills somebody. It
doesn't pay חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. So where the מועד muad pays
full, the תם tam pays zero if it kills another person. So
let's just read one more line. Meaning the difference is that there's
no חצי כופר. chatzi kofer. That normally the תם tam pays half,
here's another difference though that wasn't in this list, that when it
comes to כופר, kofer, killing a person, the תם tam actually pays
zero. The גמרא says no, אי משום חצי כופר לא שיורא הוא.
i mishum chatzi kofer lo shiyura hu. By the way, that's not
necessarily a difference because הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא ha mani
Rabbi Yose Ha-Gelili hi who says תם משלם חצי כופר. tam meshallem
chatzi kofer. There's an opinion that a תם tam does pay half
כופר. kofer. So it's not necessarily a difference. Anyway, once again we've
got the idea of a list that says differences between תם tam
and מועד, muad, it does not mention the קנס knas, idea, another
indication that the תם tam payment is money and not קנס, and
the גמרא finds a way to say it's not a complete list
and gets out of this.
Okay. ושיורא הוא מידי? veshiyura hu midi? It wasn't left off?
Yeah, it means that from the other side of the opinion, you
don't have to prove that something was left off because you can
argue that from the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it wasn't
left off. Okay. So you know,
alright, it's already 8:35, so unfortunately we're going to have to end
here and still be an עמוד behind. Okay? Unless people want to
stay another 10 minutes and finish out to the end of the
פרק. perek. Is anybody prepared to do that? Or people want to
go to דאווענינג? davening?
Fine. Alright, we will pick up tomorrow. No questions tomorrow.
I mean I'm okay if you want to go 10 minutes
later tomorrow if you're—well at least I have to...